# **ANIL BHATTARAI**

1 (416) 857 0496 | anilbhattarai@gmail.com | https://www.linkedin.com/in/anil-bhattarai-5a699b28/ | https://github.com/anilbhattaraitoronto https://dr-anil.com/

### **EXECUTIVE PROFILE**

highly diligent, self-motivated, and **fast-learning** information technology professional who has been designing and building full stack web applications since 2018. Intermediate to advanced level competence in 6 human languages (**Nepali**, **English**, **Hindi**, **French**, **Bhojpuri**, and **Spanish**) and 4 computer languages (**HTML**, **CSS**, **JavaScript** and **Python**). Key strengths include **joyful attitude towards learning**, effective communication (written and verbal), and able to deliver projects through timely and efficient processes and effective planning always with consideration of end users. Keen to leverage information technology and critical analytical and communication skills to contribute to sustainable planet with much of social activism, education, and research focused on climate change, ecological food systems, and environmental justice.

#### **EDUCATION**

### PhD in Planning (2019)

University of Toronto, Department of Geography and Planning

**Dissertation**: Seeing Like A Farmer: Socioecological Complexity of Constructing and Maintaining Smallholder Ecological Farms

## M.A. in Anthropology (2008)

University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, Department of Anthropology

Thesis: The Nature of Nepali State and Hegemony of Technocentrism and Behaviorism in Health Practices in Nepal

### M. Phil. In Social Medicine and Community Health (2002)

Jawaharlal Nehru University, Center of Social Medicine and Community Health

Thesis: From Population Control to Reproductive Rights: The Case of Nepal

# M.A. in Economics (2000)

Tribhuvan University, Department of Economics

Thesis: Conservation and Erosion of Local Livelihoods

#### **INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY**

#### Competence

### Frontend

- HTML, CSS, JavaScript, and Component-based frameworks such as React/Vue/Svelte/Sveltekit
- Progressive Web Application (PWA)

#### Backend

- Nodejs, Express, Django,
   Python, JavaScript
- Relational Database
   Management Systems
   (Sqlite, MySQL,
   PostgreSQL) with efficient database design

#### Server

- Nginx, Linux Virtual Machine (Ubuntu)
- Bash and Python Scripts for task automation
- Good understanding of Azure Cloud Services

#### **Projects**

Kelytas (kelytas.com)

• A website for a wedding dress shop based in Barrie, Ontario

eFaram (efaram.com) (under construction)

- An fullstack e-commerce platform for ecological farmers in Nepal to sell their surplus products
- A forum for sharing ecological farming knowledge and technologies among farmers

Nepal Reviewed (nepalreviewed.com)

- A Web Platform to summarize academic writings related to Nepal into Nepali language
- A platform for collaboration among globally dispersed researchers

Nepaliis (nepaliis.com)

- A web platform for writings about computing technologies in Nepali language
- A Nepali language learning web application

Chitwan Society of Canada (cscnep.com)

• A fullstack application for members to post ideas, share information about upcoming events, and renew membership of Chitwan Society of Canada

#### NON-PROFIT EMPLOYMENT

### **Drew North Consulting (Dec. 2019 – Mar. 2020)**

Election Assistant (Canadian Union of Postal Workers, Toronto Local)

• Managing electronic voter rolls, in-person voting across 20 booths, and resolving conflicts

#### Toronto Environmental Alliance (Feb.—Mar. 2018)

Research Assistant

- Collaborating with 6 other researchers in setting up tools and classifying, weighing, and disposing wastes
- Filing preliminary data generated from the research

#### Learn NC, North Carolina, Chapel Hill (Feb.—Jul. 2007)

Image Curator

- Classifying and annotating old photographs related to Nepal
- Advising Learn NC about the best possible uses of these photographs as learning materials in school curriculum

### **Action Aid International (Feb.—June 2006)**

Consultant

- Investigation of strategic issues facing Cambodian society
- Preparation of strategic plan for Action Aid program in Cambodia
- Facilitation of workshops among Action Aid staff regarding the strategic plan document

# **Nepal South Asia Center (NESAC)**

Executive Director (Aug. 2002 - Apr. 2006)

- Led the organization during Nepal's most turbulent political period
- Mentored 10 young activists working on the issues of sustainable livelihoods of fishing communities impacted by adverse nature conservation policies in Chitwan Valley of South-Central Nepal
- Managed and coordinated an international collaborative research on "Voices of Civil Societies from the South" as a National Team Leader
- Managed and coordinated "Dialogue on constitutional process in Nepal" in partnership with International Institute for Democracy and Electoral Assistance (IDEA)
- Carried out a policy research on "Responsiveness of the local political system towards poor and marginalized" funded by Department for International Development (DfID)

#### RESEARCH EMPLOYMENT

#### South Asia Institute of Advanced Studies, Kathmandu (Nov 2015 - Nov 2016)

Senior Research Fellow

- Led the field research in Nepal and India on climate change, agriculture, and air pollution
- Interviewed farmers, policy makers, environmental activists, and politicians
- Collaboratively wrote a peer-reviewed article for a prestigious journal

### University of Edinburg (Dec. 2014 – Apr. 2015)

Research Assistant (Prof. Andrea Nightingale, Department of Geography)

- Collection and detailed review of bibliographic materials related to climate change
- Collaborative preparation of outline of two journal articles

#### **University of Toronto (2008 – 2019)**

Research Assistant (Prof. Katharine Rankin, Dept. of Geography and Planning)

Preparing annotated bibliography related to social movement, neoliberal policies, and democracy

Research Assistant (Prof. Mark Hunter, Dept. of Geography and Planning)

• Preparing annotated bibliography related to labor issues in South Africa

### **University of North Carolina (May 2007 – Dec. 2007)**

Research Assistant (Prof. Lauren Leve, Department of Religion)

- Preparation of annotated bibliography related to Buddhism in Nepal
- Translation of collected Nepali language materials into English

#### **TEACHING EMPLOYMENT**

### **University of Toronto (2008 – 2019)**

Teaching Assistant (12 courses on ecology, climate change, health, and food)

• Running tutorial classes, and advising students including resolving conflicts

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### **Peer Reviewed**

Journal Articles

Estor, J, Wennstrom, P., **Bhattarai**, A., Nightingale, A.J., Eriksen, S., Sillmann, J. (2019). Asking the right questions in adaptation research and practice: Seeing beyond climate impacts in rural Nepal. *Environmental Science and Policy* vol. 94, pp.227-236. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsci.2019.01.013

Nightingale, A.; **Bhattarai**, A., Ojha, H., Sigdel, T. and Rankin, K. (2018). Fragmented public authority and state un/making in the 'new' republic of Nepal. *Modern Asian Studies*, 52(2): in press.

Bhattarai, A. (2018). Book Review (Nepali) Planning Families in Nepal, by Jan Brunson. *Samaj Adhyan*, 12:285-288. Bhattarai, A. 2017. Review of Planning Families in Nepal, Jan Brunson. Studies in Nepali History and Society. 22(1):214-217.

Book Chapters and Edited Book

Bhattarai, A. and Gautam, B. [Eds.] (2005), *Swasthya*, *Samaj ra Rajniti* (Health Society and Politics) (Nepali) Martin Chautari, Kathmandu.

Bhattarai, A. (2004) "Nepalma janasankhya niyantran" (population control in Nepal). In Deschene, M. and Onta P. [eds.] *Nepalko sandarvama samajsashtriya gyana* (Social Science Knowledge in Nepali Context) (Nepali). Social Science Baha, Kathmandu.

Bhattarai, A. (2003) "A case for radical non-violence" in Thapa, D. (Ed.) *Understanding Maoist Movement in Nepal*. Martin Chautari, Kathmandu. Pp.349-358.

#### **Policy Documents**

Bhattarai A. and Jana, S. (2005), Grassroots Organization Engaging Conservation Agency: Case Study of Indigenous Fishing Communities' Right to Fishing in South Central Nepal. London: Research and policy in Development Programme (RAPID), Overseas Development Institute. Available at <a href="https://www.odi.org/publications/2763-grassroots-organisation-engaging-conservation-agency-nepal-case-indigenous-fishing-communities">https://www.odi.org/publications/2763-grassroots-organisation-engaging-conservation-agency-nepal-case-indigenous-fishing-communities</a>

Bhattarai, A. (2005) "Promise of Democracy in Nepal." Paper prepared for State of Democracy in South Asia project coordinated by Lokniti Program of New Delhi-based Centre for the Study of Developing Societies (CSDS).

Bhattarai, A (2005). Responsiveness of Local Government Towards Poor and Marginalized: A Research Report. Submitted to Department for International Development, UK's Kathmandu Office.

### **Newspaper and Magazine Articles**

Bhattarai, A. (2004) "The word and the world." Seminar, April. http://www.india-seminar.com/2005/548/548%20anil%20bhattarai.htm accessed on 23January 2012.

Bhattarai, A. (2003) "Mysterious afflictions" July. Himal South Asian.

Over 225 editorials for *The Kathmandu Post*, largest English language daily in Nepal, and Kantipur, the largest Nepali language daily in Nepal on climate change, organic farming, democracy, ecological futures, degradations of landscape, international aid, political economy of health, among many other things. I published a weekly column called (un)commonsense for The Kathmandu Post for seven years (2009 – 2016)

#### **LANGUAGES**

- Nepali (Native mother tongue)
- English (Advanced)
- French (Advanced reading, basic writing, good speaking)
- Hindi (advanced speaking, writing, reading)
- Urdu (advanced speaking, listening)
- Spanish (basic)

#### **REFERENCES**

#### **Prof. Katharine N. Rankin**

Department of Geography and Planning, University of Toronto Phone: 1 (416) 978 1592 rankin@geog.utoronto.ca

# **Prof. Angela Miles**

Ontario Institute of Secondary Education, University of Toronto Phone:1 (416) 968 1282 angela.miles@utoronto.ca

#### **Prof. Andrea Nightingale**

Dept. of Sociology and Human Geography, University of Oslo Phone: 47 22855141 a.j.nightingale@socgeo.uio.no